Guide to the George Miller Beard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Miller Beard papers
1853-1923
MS 584
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(3 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, biographical material and other papers of George M. Beard, physician and specialist in the treatment of mental and nervous disorders. Included are materials relating to his work on the medical uses of electricity and his pioneering work in the definition of criminal insanity, as well as papers relating to his interest in spiritualism. Also included are a number of letters received by his daughter, Grace Alden Beard, related to a biographical study of her father.
Beard, George M. (George Miller), 1839-1883
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. George Beard Walker in 1970.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Subject File.
Scope and Contents
The George Miller Beard Papers provide limited but valuable information on the life and work of Beard from 1865 to 1883. Though incomplete, they do provide a sampling of his work on nervous diseases, electrotherapeutics, insanity, and spiritualism. Newspaper clippings, photographs, and printed biographical articles shed additional light upon Beard's career. There are also legal briefs, testimony, and newsclippings relating to Beard's views on criminal insanity, as well as material on some of the spectacular cases of the day, such as the Guiteau murder trial, the Henry Prouse Cooper case, and the Cadet Whittaker case. Of special interest is an essay by Beard's daughter, Grace A. Beard, on the upbringing of a child in the nineteenth century.
Correspondence forms a small part of the papers and gives little information upon such intriguing subjects as Beard's collaboration with Thomas Edison or his experiments in London on spiritualism. There, are, however, a few letters from such notable men as Wendell Phillips, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Rev. Joseph Cooke, Thomas Edison, William Crookes, D. B. St. John Roosa, and Lester Ward. In addition, there are important letters in the correspondence of his daughter, Grace. Orphaned at the age of seven, when both of her parents died within one week of each other, she attempted to satisfy her curiosity about her father's life and works, especially his work in spiritualism, by corresponding with many of his colleagues and contemporaries. The most notable of these are: Simon E. Baldwin, Professor William Henry Brewer, Charles L. Dana, Timothy Dwight, Thomas Edison, and Alfred R. Wallace.
The George Miller Beard Papers were donated to Yale University by Mr. and Mrs. George Beard Walker in 1970. Mr. Walker is the grandson of George M. Beard and the son of Grace Alden Beard. The originals of the photo-copies were returned to Mr. and Mrs. Walker after the copies were made.
Biographical / Historical
George Miller Beard, 1839-1883, was a distinguished physician and specialist in the treatment of mental and nervous disorders. He was born in Montville, Connecticut, the son of the Reverend Spencer F. Beard, a Congregational clergyman, and Lucy A. Leonard. He entered Yale College in 1858, graduated in Arts in 1862, and spent a year in the Yale Medical Department before studying at the College of Physicians and Surgeons in New York. Qualifying in 1866, Beard immediately joined Dr. A. D. Rockwell in practice in New York, and began to specialize in the study of nervous diseases.
With A. D. Rockwell, Beard published many works on the use of electricity in medical treatment. These studies resulted in the isolation of a complaint, nervous exhaustion or neurasthenia, to which, as Beard explained in his book, American Nervousness(1881), Americans seemed particularly susceptible. Beard also attributed hay-fever, sea sickness, and certain sexual problems to nervous disorders.
Beard championed the rights of the insane and was instrumental in the formation of the "National Association for the Protection of the Insane and Prevention of Insanity." He worked to reform the law so that the insane could not be found guilty of crime, and was famous for vigorously defending this opinion in the case of Charles J. Guiteau, the assassin of President Garfield.
Interested in spiritualism, Beard carried out many experiments in order to prove his theory that mind reading, trances and other manifestations of spiritualism had physiological explanations. His demonstrations at medical association conferences seem to have excited considerable controversy.
Beard died at the age of 44, but during his short life he was a prolific writer and an active campaigner for medical and social causes. His works range from those with a popular appeal, such as Our Home Physician, to scholarly treatises, like the Medical Use of Electricity. Beard's attention to original and frequently unusual research opened up a field of medicine which had been generally neglected until that time. His works were written with vigor and sometimes with unpleasant bluntness, but he was praised after his death in 1883 by a colleague, William Crookes, as "one of that rare class of thinkers who dare to utter their thoughts, and who discuss matters to which the world is glad to close its eyes."
Biographical material may be found in SERIES I, folder 20; and SERIES III, folder 2.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Electricity; Electrotherapeutics; Hysteria; Insanity (Law); Law; Medicine; Mental illness; Nervous system -- Diseases; Neurasthenia; Older people -- Employment; Popular culture; Psychology, Pathological; Psychoses; Sexual disorders; Spiritualism; Physicians; Baldwin, Simeon E. (Simeon Eben), 1840-1927; Beard, Elizabeth Alden; Beard, George M. (George Miller), 1839-1883; Beard, Grace Alden; Beard, Lucy Leonard; Beard, Spencer F.; Brewer, William Henry, 1828-1910; Cooke, Joseph Brown, 1868-; Crookes, William, 1832-1919; Dana, Charles L. (Charles Loomis), 1852-1935; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931; Guiteau, Charles J. (Charles Julius), 1841-1882; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Phillips, Wendell, 1811-1884; Roosa, D. B. St. John (Daniel Bennett St. John), 1838-1908; Wallace, Alfred Russel, 1823-1913; Ward, Lester F. (Lester Frank), 1841-1913
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1853-1923; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is arranged in three subsections:
  "Family Correspondence," 1854-1883, includes letters to Elizabeth Beard (his wife) before their marriage and also during and enforced separation (1880) after their marriage. The letters from his parents give some insight into the religious influences under which Beard grew up. This section is arranged alphabetically either by the name of the person to whom the letter is addressed or by the name of the writer of the letter.
  "General Correspondence of George M. Beard," 1871-1883, includes letters Beard received from colleagues, patients, and others interested in his work, including those notable correspondents previously noted.
  "Correspondence of Grace A. Beard," 1883-1923, contains correspondence pertaining to Beard, which Grace Beard (his daughter) planned to use in publishing the biography and complete works of her father.
  - Family Correspondence
    - Beard, Elizabeth (née Alden) -- from G. M. Beard, 1862-1864, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Beard, Elizabeth (née Alden) -- general, 1864-1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Beard, Grace A. Beard, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Beard, Lucy L. (mother), 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Beard, S. F. (father), 1854-1866 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Beard, William, -- correspondence, 1863-1866 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cornith, (Mrs.) S. H. (sister) -- letters, 1904, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 6a)
    - Miscellaneous -- not involving G. M. Beard (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence
    - Beard, G. M. -- professional, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bastian H. Charlton, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Batsford C. C., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Benedikt Prof. Dr., 1876 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Blake L. D., 1874 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bryce, P., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Burnside, G. L., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Colfax, R., 1871 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Cook, Joseph, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Crookes, William, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Denslow, V?. B., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Edison, Thomas A. (copy), 1878 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Farnswoth, G. A., 1875 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell (copy), 1882 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Leavitt, William, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Phillips, Wendell, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Roosa, D. B. St. John, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Ward, Lester F., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - White, Horace, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notes on spiritualistic manifestations; 2 letters on exposure of spiritualists, 1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence of Grace Alden Beard
    - Abbe, Robert, 1904-1908 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Beard, Grace A., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Baldwin, Simeon E., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Blyndenburgh, L. N., 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Brewer, Prof. William H., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Burkes, Henry T., 1908 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Dana, Charles L., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Draper, Ellen Childs, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Dwight, Timothy, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Edison, Thomas (copy) -- also letters by Dyer in behalf of Edison, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Henslow, G., 1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Holt, Henry, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lindsley, C. Purdy, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Moll, Albert, 1910-1923 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Morrow, Prince A., 1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Rockwell, A. D., 1883-1894 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Roosa, D. B. St. John, 1904-1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Stevens, Edward L., 1909 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Tracy, Roger S., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Walker, Jerome, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Wallace, Alfred R., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - unidentified, 1904-1908 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- WRITINGS, 1856-1883; Series II
  WRITINGS include a diary of Beard's early life (1856-1863), lectures, articles, 18 pamphlets, and a book. The series is arranged alphabetically by category and chronologically within each category.
  Although all of Beard's work is not included, there is a good sample of his work on the use of electrotherapeutics in medical treatment, nervous diseases, the insane, and spiritualism. Of special interest are Beard's notes on the lives of 400 famous men for his essay, "The Relation of Age and Work."
  - Advertisements, book notices etc., 1875-1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book, American Nervousness — Its Causes and Consequences (copy), 1881 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1856-1863 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Experiments on Hayfever, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lectures -- annotated in The Medical and Surgical Reporter, 1867-1870 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lectures and articles (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Hysteria and Allied Affections,", 1872 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "American Nervousness,", 1880 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Disease,", 1882 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Medical Education and the Medical Profession,", 1883 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lectures (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Experiences with a Life Insurance Agent,", undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Nervous Disease,", undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "The Relation of Age to Work" discussion of, by Grace Beard, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Essay on Lecturing -- humorous, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Cases of Gastralgia treated by Central Galvanism,", 1872 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "A Plea for Scientific Reform,", 1872 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Atmospheric Electricity and Ozone,", 1874 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Suggestive Cases treated by Electricity,", 1874 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Medical and Surgical Cases treated by Electricity,", 1874 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Marasmus, Whooping-Cough and Debility in Children,", 1874 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Treating Malignant Tumors by Electrolysing the Base,", 1874 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Experiments with the Alledged New Force,", 1876 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Practical Points in Electrolytic Treatment,", 1877 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Are Inebriates Automatons?,", 1878 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Neurasthenia (Nervous Exhaustion) as a Cause of Inebriety,", 1879 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The Dosage of Electricity,", 1879 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "A Practical Treatise on Neurasthenia" (in German), 1880 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Nervous Exhaustion, with Cases of Sexual Neurasthenia,", 1880 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Notes on Sexual Neurasthenia,", 1880 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Copies of the last two pamphlets enclosed in wrapper for special distribution, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "How to Use Bromides,", 1881 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Trance and Muscle Reading,", 1882 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Herbert Spencer on American Nervousness,", 1883 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Galley Proofs of the above pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Research notes for "The Relation of Age and Work" (1) undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Research notes for "The Relation of Age and Work" (2) undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1862-1883, 1966, undated; Series III; 0.5; (1 box)
  The SUBJECT FILE is divided into two subsections, "General," and "Case Studies."
  "General" contains Published biographical articles, photographs, and newspaper clippings. This section is arranged alphabetically by subject. "Case Studies" includes court testimony and briefs, newspaper clippings, and papers pertaining to Beard's interest in the defense of Guiteau, President Garfield's murderer. This section is arranged chronologically.
  - General Biographical Material
    - Autograph book -- Phillips Academy, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Conferences, journeys etc., 1879-1880 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Deaths of George M. Beard and Elizabeth Beard, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Essays by Grace A. Beard (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Funeral address by Rev. J. L. Willard (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - General biographical material collected by Grace Beard, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper cuttings, articles etc, collected by George M. Beard, 1881-1882 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Photographs and personal belongings, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Printed biographies, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Recent articles, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Special Case Studies
    - Spiritualism -- Fancher case, 1878 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Guiteau case -- newspaper cuttings, 1881-1882 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Guiteau case -- other papers, 1881-1882 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Henry Prouse Cooper case, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Cadet Whittaker case, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Additional Material, ACCESSION 1887-M-028
  - Letters to Jared A. Terry, 1862-1866 (Box 3, Folder 14)